of this masterpiece to reveal what could have been underneath. Well, this happens to be the most important painting we have in Italy by Leonardo da Vinci, and look at the wonderful images of faces that nobody has seen for five centuries. Look at these portraits. They're magnificent. You see Leonardo at work. You see the geniality of his creation, right directly on the ground layer of the panel, and see this cool thing, finding, I should rather say, an elephant. (Laughter) Because of this elephant, over 70 new images came out, never seen for centuries. This was an epiphany. We came to understand and to prove that the brown coating that we see today was not done by Leonardo da Vinci, which left us only the other drawing that for five centuries we were not able to see, so thanks only to technology. Well, the tablet. Well, we thought, well, if we all have this pleasure, this privilege to see all this, to find all these discoveries, what about for everybody else? So we thought of an augmented reality application using a tablet. Let me show you just simulating what we could be doing, any of us could be doing, in a museum environment. So let's say that we go to a museum with a tablet, okay? And we just aim the camera of the tablet to the painting that we are interested to see, like this. Okay? And I will just click on it, we pause, and now let me turn to you so the moment the image, or, I should say, the camera, has locked in the painting, then the images you just saw up there in the drawing are being loaded. And so, see. We can, as we said, we can zoom in. Then we can scroll. Okay? Let's go and find the elephant. So all we need is one finger. Just wipe off and we see the elephant. (Applause) (Applause) Okay? And then if we want, we can continue the scroll to find out, for example, on the staircase, the whole iconography is going to be changed. There are a lot of laymen reconstructing from the ruins of an old temple a new temple, and there are a lot of figures showing up. See? This is not just a curiosity, because it changes not just the iconography as you see it, but the iconology, the meaning of the painting, and we believe this is a cool way, easy way, that everybody could have access to, to become more the protagonist of your own discovery, and not just be so passive about it, as we are when we walk through endless rooms of museums. (Applause) Another concept is the digital clinical chart, which sounds very obvious if we were to talk about real patients, but when we talk about works of art, unfortunately, it's never been tapped as an idea. Well, we believe, again, that this should be the beginning, the very first step, to do real conservation, and allowing us to really explore and to understand everything related to the state of our conservation, the technique, materials, and also if, when, and why we should restore, or, rather, to intervene on the environment surrounding the painting. Well, our vision is to rediscover the spirit of the Renaissance, create a new discipline where engineering for cultural heritage is actually a symbol of blending art and science together. We definitely need a new breed of engineers that will go out and do this kind of work and rediscover for us these values, these cultural values that we badly need, especially today. And if you want to summarize in one just single word, well, this is what we're trying to do. We're trying to give a future to our past in order to have a future. As long as we live a life of curiosity and passion, there is a bit of Leonardo in all of us. Thank you. (Applause) (Applause)
de la obra maestra y revelar lo que podría haber debajo. Esta resultó ser la pintura más importante que tenemos en Italia de Leonardo da Vinci y miren estas hermosas imágenes de rostros que nadie ha visto en cinco siglos. Miren estos retratos. Son magníficos. Se ve a Leonardo en acción. Se ve la genialidad de su creación, directamente en la capa base del panel, y ver esta genialidad y encontrar —-diría más bien—- un elefante. (Risas) Gracias a este elefante, aparecieron más de 70 imágenes nuevas, nunca vistas en siglos. Fue una revelación. Llegamos a entender y demostrar que el revestimiento marrón que vemos hoy no pertenece a Leonardo da Vinci, que nos dejó sólo los otros dibujos, que durante cinco siglos no pudimos ver y hoy lo vemos gracias a la tecnología. Bien, la tableta. Bueno, pensamos, tenemos el placer, el privilegio de ver todo esto, de hallar estos descubrimientos, ¿y si lo compartimos con los demás? Por eso pensamos en una aplicación de realidad aumentada en una tableta. Les mostraré un simulacro de lo que podríamos hacer, cualquiera de nosotros, en un museo. Supongamos que vamos a un museo con una tableta, ¿sí? Y apuntamos con la cámara de la tableta a la pintura que nos interesa ver, por ejemplo ésta. ¿Sí? Haré clic, apretaré pausa, y ahora vuelvo a Uds. y en el momento en que la imagen o —-debería decir la cámara-—- capturó la pintura, se cargaron las imágenes que vieron allí arriba en el dibujo. Así que vean. Podemos, como decíamos, ampliarla. Y luego desplazarnos. ¿Sí? Vayamos a descubrir el elefante. Todo lo que necesitamos es un dedo. Limpiamos y vemos el elefante. (Aplausos) (Aplausos) ¿Sí? Y si queremos podemos seguir desplazándonos para encontrar, por ejemplo en la escalera, que toda la iconografía va a cambiar. Hay una gran cantidad de laicos reconstruyendo, de las ruinas de un viejo templo, un nuevo templo y aparecen un montón de figuras. ¿Las ven? Esto no es sólo una curiosidad, sino que cambia no sólo la iconografía tal como la ven, sino la iconología, el significado de la pintura, y creemos que esta es una manera genial, muy fácil, de que todo el mundo tenga acceso a, se vuelva más protagonista del propio descubrimiento y no un mero espectador pasivo, como lo somos al recorrer las salas interminables de los museos. (Aplausos) Otro concepto es la historia clínica digital, que suena muy obvia si hablamos de pacientes reales pero si se trata de obras de arte, desafortunadamente, nunca lo hemos considerado. Bueno nuevamente creemos que esto debería ser el comienzo, el primer paso hacia la conservación real que nos permita realmente explorar y entender todo lo relacionado al estado de nuestra conservación, la técnica, los materiales y también si, cuándo y por qué deberíamos restaurar o, mejor dicho, intervenir el entorno que circunda a la pintura. Nuestra visión es redescubrir el espíritu del Renacimiento; crear una nueva disciplina en la que la ingeniería del patrimonio cultural sea en realidad un símbolo de la amalgama entre arte y ciencia. Definitivamente necesitamos una nueva generación de ingenieros dispuestos a hacer este tipo de trabajo y redescubrir estos valores, estos valores culturales que tanto necesitamos, en especial hoy. Si queremos resumirlo en una palabra, esto es lo que tratamos de hacer: tratamos de darle un futuro a nuestro pasado para tener un futuro. En tanto vivamos una vida de curiosidad y pasión, habrá un poco de Leonardo en cada uno de nosotros. Gracias. (Aplausos) (Aplausos)